<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://frantic.im/</id>
  <title>frantic.im</title>
  <link rel="self" href="https://frantic.im/feed.xml" />
  <icon>https://frantic.im/favicon.png</icon>
  <subtitle>Occasional posts on technology and stuff</subtitle>
  <updated>2025-12-28T18:10:54.159Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Alex Kotliarskyi</name>
  </author>

  
    <entry>
      <id>https://frantic.im/remix-3</id>
      <title>Thoughts on Remix 3</title>
      <updated>2025-10-12T12:00:00+00:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://frantic.im/remix-3" />
      <summary>The pendulum is about to swing the other direction</summary>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        
        
        
        <p><a href="https://remix.run/">Remix</a> is a web framework by <s>React underdogs</s> authors of the most popular React package. A few days ago at <a href="https://remix.run/jam/2025">Remix Jam 2025</a>, Ryan and Michael shared a sneak peek of Remix v3. There’s no official blog post or documentation yet. Here’s my attempt at explaining what it is about.</p>
<p>Remix v1 was a React framework that managed data loading and server-side rendering. Its biggest achievement was the <a href="https://remix.run/">marketing website</a>. Early Remix was interesting because it was viewed as the first real contender for Next.js’s dominant position.</p>
<p>Remix v2 struggled with its messaging and identity. One of the authors <a href="https://x.com/ryanflorence/status/1791479313939976313">described it</a> as <em>“Remix v2 is a Vite plugin that makes access to React Router v6 features more convenient through the Route Module API”</em>. This is definitely not how you beat Vercel’s marketing machine. The framework had its users, but definitely not the trajectory to make a dent in Next.js’s market share.</p>
<p>Remix v3 is… very different. It represents a broader shift in web development sentiment and could be worth paying attention to. To understand why, let’s look at the state of modern React.</p>
<h2>Modern React</h2>
<p><strong>In 2025, React feels complicated.</strong> React Server Components introduced a more sophisticated way to render components on the server and hydrate them on client. The rules of what is allowed are nuanced: server components can be defined as <code>async</code> now and pass data to client components (but not all kinds of data). Regular server-side functions can now be used on client via magic RPC actions. Developers need to learn <a href="https://react.dev/reference/rsc/use-client"><code>&quot;use client&quot;</code></a> vs <a href="https://react.dev/reference/rsc/use-server"><code>&quot;use server&quot;</code></a>.</p>
<p>The speed, especially on big apps, started to be a common concern. Frameworks like Svelte introduced a way to sidestep virtual DOM diffing and produce the most efficient direct way of updating elements, while still looking reasonably declarative. So the React team opened access to the React compiler, a project that has been brewing up inside Meta for almost 8 years. It works by auto-memoizing your components and hooks. But not all components, because that could introduce subtle bugs. Now it’s about <a href="https://react.dev/reference/react-compiler/directives/use-memo"><code>&quot;use memo&quot;</code></a> and <a href="https://react.dev/reference/react-compiler/directives/use-no-memo"><code>&quot;use no memo&quot;</code></a> (aliased as <code>&quot;use forget&quot;</code> and <code>&quot;use no forget&quot;</code> which doesn’t help with the confusion).</p>
<p>The core API surface of React keeps growing. React has added async rendering APIs (<a href="https://react.dev/reference/react/Suspense"><code>Suspense</code></a>, <a href="https://react.dev/reference/react/startTransition"><code>startTransition</code></a>, <a href="https://react.dev/reference/react/useDeferredValue"><code>useDeferredValue</code></a>, <a href="https://react.dev/reference/react/useActionState"><code>useActionState</code></a>) to make web apps more responsive – now user interactions can be prioritized against less urgent but expensive component tree updates, but require you to reason about “active” and “pending” states. The other new APIs are also seen as complex and niche. Just look at the documentation for <a href="https://react.dev/reference/react/useEffectEvent"><code>useEffectEvent</code></a> (but try to guess what it’s doing before you click).</p>
<p><strong>Nobody forces developers to use these features.</strong> In fact even the oldest <code>createReactClass</code> with mixins work just fine with the official <code>create-react-class</code> npm package. You can still use that style of React today, you don’t have to adopt any of the new modern features.</p>
<p>Except, <a href="https://react.dev/learn/creating-a-react-app">you kind of have to</a> – these features are shoved into developers’ throats via <a href="https://nextjs.org/">Next.js</a>. React itself gave up attempts at being a framework. It was just too much work to keep up with fast paced JS tooling, and Facebook had their own setup not worth opensourcing.</p>
<p>Next.js itself went through some painful transitions (<a href="https://nextjs.org/docs/pages">pages router</a> vs <a href="https://nextjs.org/docs/app/getting-started">app router</a>) and left developers who live on the bleeding edge badly hurt. On top of the API churn, Next.js has a whole another layer of complexity caused by Vercel. Vercel deploys fullstack Next.js apps in its own special way – some code runs in the browser, some in AWS Lambda (with 3x markup), and some in its proprietary worker runtime (“middleware” must be one of the biggest lies that caused developer-decades of confusion and frustration).</p>
<p>All this stuff is just… too much. In fact, even explaining the problems these features and frameworks are trying to fix took Dan several <a href="https://overreacted.io/react-for-two-computers/">conferences</a> and <a href="https://overreacted.io/the-two-reacts/">blog posts</a> to describe. People who get it, get it. RSC, Suspense, React Compiler are really powerful and solve real problems some companies have.</p>
<p>On top of that, LLMs suck at React. When asked to build an app, they all reach for React, but the resulting components are ugly soups of <code>useEffects</code> and random hacks to work around subtle bugs.</p>
<h2>Remix v3</h2>
<p>So in this state of complexity and frustration, Remix v3 is born. You can watch the <a href="https://remix.run/jam/2025">Remix Jam</a> recording (look for timestamps in the comments) + scroll through both authors’ X accounts to get a sense of it.</p>
<p>On the frontend Remix still uses JSX, but there’s no React runtime. It doesn’t track state the way React does, but instead gives developers a <code>this.update()</code> function to call to tell Remix that something has changed. Instead of explicit state you can use anything, most commonly closure-captured variables:</p>
<pre><code class="language-typescript"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">Counter</span>(<span class="hljs-params"><span class="hljs-variable language_">this</span>: Remix.Handle</span>) {
  <span class="hljs-comment">// State is just a closure</span>
  <span class="hljs-keyword">let</span> count = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>;

  <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="hljs-function">() =&gt;</span> (
    <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span>
      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span>{count}<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span>
      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">button</span>
        <span class="hljs-attr">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;p-2 text-green-500&quot;</span>
        <span class="hljs-attr">on</span>=<span class="hljs-string">{dom.click((event,</span> <span class="hljs-attr">signal</span>) =&gt;</span> {
          count++;
          this.update();
        })}
      &gt;
        Inc
      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">button</span>&gt;</span>
    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span>
  );
}
</code></pre>
<p>This makes code more imperative, mechanically simpler. Do this, then do that. Transitions, instead of React’s promise of <code>view = f(state)</code>.</p>
<p>Events are first class and use web’s built-in events mechanism. Instead of <code>onClick</code> there’s a universal <code>&quot;on&quot;</code> prop and a library of standard <code>dom</code> events + developers can define their own <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/CustomEvent"><code>CustomEvents</code></a>.</p>
<p>To control async work, Remix relies on <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/AbortController/signal">signals</a>. E.g. to cancel a <code>fetch</code> when component unmounts the developers can do this:</p>
<pre><code>function Cities(this: Remix.Handle) {
  let list = [], isLoading = true;
  fetch(&quot;https://api.remix.run/cities.json&quot;, {
    signal: this.signal // &lt;-
  })
    .then(response =&gt; response.json())
    .then(data =&gt; {
      list = data;
      isLoading = false;
      this.update();
    });

  return () =&gt; …
}
</code></pre>
<p>Remix will ship with a component library. React has a wide ecosystem of components that won’t work in Remix, so to stay competitive the team is working on high quality built-in components. Things like menus and forms with attention to detail and accessibility support. It also introduces subtle but nice quality-of-life improvements over React: built-in <code>css</code> prop, <code>class</code> instead of <code>className</code>.</p>
<p>On the backend, Remix double-downs on Web Platform. The handlers take web <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Request"><code>Request</code></a> and return <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Response"><code>Response</code></a>. It also brings things like <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/FormData"><code>FormData</code></a>, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/File"><code>File</code></a> and others to the server. This makes the server runtime an implementation detail. Node, Deno, Bun – all have either native support or adapters for these web APIs, so Remix can run anywhere.</p>
<p>In v3 the framework gave up on file-based routing. Just too much trouble to capture the range of things they want to support in just the file names. Instead it introduces a TypeScript-based way of defining the routes. TypeScript guarantees all routes are implemented and URL parameters are passed to handlers and links are never broken.</p>
<pre><code class="language-typescript"><span class="hljs-keyword">let</span> routes = <span class="hljs-title function_">route</span>({
  <span class="hljs-attr">home</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;/&quot;</span>,
  <span class="hljs-attr">about</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;/about&quot;</span>,
  <span class="hljs-attr">books</span>: {
    <span class="hljs-attr">index</span>: { <span class="hljs-attr">method</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;GET&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-attr">pattern</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;/&quot;</span> },
    <span class="hljs-attr">create</span>: { <span class="hljs-attr">method</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;POST&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-attr">pattern</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;/&quot;</span> },
    <span class="hljs-attr">show</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;/books/:slug&quot;</span>,
  },
});

<span class="hljs-comment">// Implementation on server</span>
router.<span class="hljs-title function_">map</span>(routes.<span class="hljs-property">books</span>, booksHandlers)

<span class="hljs-comment">// Reference on clients</span>
&lt;a href={routes.<span class="hljs-property">home</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">href</span>()}&gt;…&lt;/a&gt;;
</code></pre>
<p>The server also comes with built-in sane things like logging and file storage.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zqhE-CepH2g">The gap</a> is what happens between the client and the server. Remix v3’s approach feels a lot less magical than RSC. There’s no custom JSON hydration streams. Instead Remix reinvents iFrames by creating async loading boundaries and uses HTML as wire format, <a href="https://htmx.org/">HTMX</a>-style. There are also hints of using <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Web_components">Web Components</a> to bring together HTML and JS.</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>Remix keeps leaning into the Web Platform and TypeScript, takes control of a wider portion of the full stack, ditches nuanced parts of React for a simple <code>this.update()</code>, which makes the code less magical and easier to understand for humans and LLMs. Remix is the <a href="https://grugbrain.dev/">Grug Brain</a> version of what Next.js should have been.</p>
<p>So what happens next?</p>
<p>You’ll hear a lot of noise and hot takes (including this post). YouTube influencers are already recording videos and generating surprised faces for video thumbnails to try to take advantage of the next hype wave. Grumpy Hacker News will complain about yet another JS framework.</p>
<p>It will seem like you have to learn Remix now and migrate all your projects to it. You don’t. React is still fine (nobody got fired for choosing React) and you can keep using the good parts (seems to be a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/JavaScript-Good-Parts-Douglas-Crockford/dp/0596517742">common JS thing</a>).</p>
<p>Remix v3 is a signal of stronger <a href="https://cassidoo.co/post/annoyed-at-react/">frustrations</a> in React community and desire for a change. The functional ↔ imperative pendulum is starting to swing the other direction.</p>
<p><img src="/figma/og_remix.png" alt="" /></p>

      ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://frantic.im/music-player</id>
      <title>A Side Project Story: Music Player</title>
      <updated>2025-10-11T12:00:00+00:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://frantic.im/music-player" />
      <summary>One of my most successful side projects had exactly 2 daily active users.</summary>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        
        
        
        <p>One of my most successful side projects had exactly 2 daily active users.</p>
<p>When I was growing up I loved listening to music, especially my parents’ cassette tapes and CDs. Back then music had a physical form. You had to take a magical artifact and carefully put it into a special machine that would produce sounds.</p>
<p>My kids growing up experience none of that. From their perspective, we do something with our phones and music just appears from a speaker. The cause and effect far apart.</p>
<p>I wanted to change that. I wanted to give them agency over what’s playing, and create an association between a physical medium, label, picture and song.</p>
<p>So here are the principles I had in mind:</p>
<ul>
<li>One physical object == one song</li>
<li>Adding new songs should be cheap and easy</li>
</ul>
<p>I did a brief research online and couldn’t find anything that fits the requirements. And I’ll be honest – I was delighted, it meant I can actually craft something novel and useful for my family and not just buy off-the-shelf solution.</p>
<p>A few days later, I had the “Music Player” (this was way before I started understanding that a good name is important). Each record was an RFID card with an image and title printed on it. You had to take this simple artifact, tap it at a special device and the music would play.</p>
<p><img src="/figma/music_player_components.png" alt="Components of the project: RFID cards, Raspberry Pi, Spotify and Sonos" /></p>
<p>It was powered by an old Raspberry Pi, simple RFID card reader and my existing Sonos speaker. Spotify served as the music library, and adding new songs there was very easy. Here’s how it worked.</p>
<p>The playback part was pretty <a href="https://github.com/frantic/miniplayer/blob/master/scripts/daemon.js">simple</a>: read RFID tag, find a song, send it to play on Sonos (this was the simplest setup because we already had an old Sonos speaker that we used for playing music).</p>
<p>But what made this project successful was how easy it was to add new songs. When we found a song we liked we’d just add it to a playlist on Spotify.</p>
<p>Which brings me to the secret sauce – the admin panel (not an overkill, I promise). It was a React app that used Spotify API to pull a list of songs from a hardcoded playlist ID. It compared the list with the existing database (stored in Firebase) of RFID ID &lt;&gt; song ID mapping, and if the song was missing from the DB, it would pull artwork, name and artist information from the song metadata. Then it rendered the grid of new songs that had a printer-friendly layout that I printed on a sticker paper, cut into individual labels and stuck them to new RFID cards. Then I used a separate RFID card reader plugged into my computer to quickly associate each card with corresponding song.</p>
<p>This process took me about 10 minutes and my kids would help with it too! After a year we had more than 200 RFID-records.</p>
<p>My kids played music on this Music Player every day for years. The youngest user was less than one year old and barely walked, but took no time to learn that tapping with a card plays the song that’s pictured on the card.</p>
<p>Many friends (with families) that visited our house asked for a system like that. I gave them the instructions but nobody ended up building it. I can’t blame them – this project can feel like too much work to fit into a busy parenting life. If you want to try, the source code (with the shopping list of materials) is here <a href="https://github.com/frantic/miniplayer">https://github.com/frantic/miniplayer</a>.</p>
<p>I loved building it, and my 2 favorite customers loved using it.</p>
<p>P.S. As I was polishing this post I saw a <a href="https://fulghum.io/album-cards">similar project by Jordan Fulghum</a>, he used NFC tags &amp; Plex instead of RFIDs &amp; Spotify. Check it out!</p>

      ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://frantic.im/get-your-shit-together-day</id>
      <title>The Get Your Shit Together Day</title>
      <updated>2025-09-18T12:00:00+00:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://frantic.im/get-your-shit-together-day" />
      <summary>Everyone needs a Get Your Shit Together day every once in a while...</summary>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        
        
        
        <p>The Get Your Shit Together day is a day off you take from work, family and other obligations.</p>
<p>It’s a day you dedicate fully to things you’ve been always postponing. Fix squeaky door hinges, repot your plant, publish that blog post, start a side project. Really anything on your todo list that has been there for years.</p>
<p>On the Get Your Shit Together day you are not allowed to work on anything typically considered urgent or important. There’s a whole life-worth of days for that.</p>
<p>The Get Your Shit Together day feels good because you finally take action on things that have been eating up on you for so long. Action creates motivation. Motivation makes you want to do more things.</p>
<p>If you read this far and this idea resonates with you, pick a random day next month and block your calendar. I promise it’ll be worth it.</p>

      ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://frantic.im/caring-about-software-quality-is-getting-harder</id>
      <title>Who Cares</title>
      <updated>2025-03-30T12:00:00+00:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://frantic.im/caring-about-software-quality-is-getting-harder" />
      <summary></summary>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        
        
        
        <p>In 2017 I gave a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fjS5ssBn3fA">talk</a> at Chain React about building great user experiences with React Native. At the time the tech was new and the quality of the mobile apps built with React Native was poor. The gist of my talk was that it’s possible to build great apps with React Native, one just needs to care enough.</p>
<p>My message didn’t resonate as well as I’d hoped. It’s hard to make people care about quality when the measuring stick of the technology is “look how fast I made this cross-platform app”. In contrast, inside the early iOS dev community, caring for quality was something that everyone shared.</p>
<p>The modern generation of users grew up without knowing what it feels like to use an offline, low-latency, well-crafted apps and websites. There’s little incentive now to spend any resources on improving quality, while your competition spends it on more features and ads.</p>
<p>I love my AI tools. They cured me from <a href="https://frantic.im/side-projects-are-hard">the blank page curse</a>, they help me learn new tech much faster, and produce boring boilerplate code.</p>
<p>But they also make it easier than ever to not care about quality…</p>

      ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://frantic.im/hn-stack</id>
      <title>The Hacker News Stack</title>
      <updated>2025-01-28T12:00:00+00:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://frantic.im/hn-stack" />
      <summary>If you want to build a web app The Hacker News Way, here's the stack you should use.</summary>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        
        
        
        <p>If you want to build a web app The Hacker News Way, here’s the stack you should use:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rust</strong> – the only language that gives you the privilege of calling your app <em>“blazing fast”</em>. According to the undocumented Hacker News rules, any post mentioning Rust in the title starts with 10 points.</li>
<li><strong>Postgres</strong> – the most beloved database that can do absolutely everything: manage data, handle row-level authorization, run job queues, replace Redis, vacuum your apartment (or its own tables… who cares?). No ORMs allowed.</li>
<li><strong>HTMX</strong> – because JavaScript is obviously the worst part about web development. Bonus points: you get to call yourself the <a href="https://htmx.org/essays/lore/#htmx-ceo">CEO of HTMX</a>, very helpful in this turbulent job market.</li>
<li><strong>Hetzner</strong> – for just $4.59/mo you can get a server that can easily handle HN’s famous <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20147951">hug-of-death</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Make sure you build your app while WFH, commuting to the office was invented by evil corporations.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>If this post made your smile, maybe you should cut down on reading Hacker News. I know I should.</p>

      ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://frantic.im/best-tool</id>
      <title>No Best Tool for the Job</title>
      <updated>2024-06-19T12:00:00+00:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://frantic.im/best-tool" />
      <summary>How do you choose the best tool for the job?</summary>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        
        
        
        <p>How do you choose the best tool for the job?</p>
<p>Suppose you want to plant a tree in your backyard and need to dig a hole. You go to the nearby hardware supply store and see these options:</p>
<p><img src="/figma/graden_tools_options.png" alt="" /></p>
<p>You don’t have to be a PhD in Gardening to know which tool is best for the job. It’s self-evident from the size of the tool and its cost.</p>
<p>The next day you decide to build a web app. You go to a catalog of website-building tools and you see this:</p>
<p><img src="/figma/web_app_tools_options.png" alt="" /></p>
<p>Let’s imagine for a moment that you are relatively new to programming. How would you pick the best tool for the job here?</p>
<h2>All these programming tools look the same</h2>
<p>Unlike tools for digging holes, all these websites look the same. They all promise the same thing — build your web app. It’s not clear why you’d pick one tool over the other. So you dig a little deeper…</p>
<h2>Infinite fractal of categorization</h2>
<p>…and discover an almost infinite amount of specialization. With hardware tools, the categories are more defined: here’s a shovel, and here’s an excavator. There’s nothing in between. With programming languages and frameworks, for any two tools, there seems to be another tool in between.</p>
<p>The job of evaluating the tools becomes harder than the job of actually using the tool.</p>
<p>You could just pick any tool and get started, but…</p>
<h2>Too easy to choose the wrong tool</h2>
<p>With hardware tools, the price and the size of the tool give you a strong hint of what it is best for. Sure, using an excavator to dig a hole for a tree sounds like a ton of fun, but buying or renting one is way too expensive. Plus, you need to learn how to drive one, get a license, and it definitely doesn’t fit into your backyard.</p>
<p>With software tools, it costs almost nothing to choose the wrong tool for the job. They all optimize for getting started quickly. Building a static website with GraphQL — easy. Use Kafka for a one-person backoffice app — no problem. You can spin up both in under 5 minutes, for free.</p>
<p>So how are you supposed to make a good choice for your web app? Well, you could search for some advice on Reddit, X, or HackerNews…</p>
<h2>Advice overload</h2>
<p>…and get overwhelmed with the amount of opposite opinions. “React is the best” / “React is the worst”, you should always render things on the server, you should make a single page app, use static types, use dynamic types, functional programming is the way, functional programming is too slow. The list of contradictions goes on and on.</p>
<p>The people shouting the advice sound extremely confident. If you dig deeper, some of them are actually employed by the tech stack they are preaching, but even outside of obvious economic incentives, it’s just too much noise to sort through.</p>
<p>Meta advice is just as polarized. “Pick a tool you already know” vs “learn new things”, “choose a popular tech stack with a large community” vs “choose niche tech stack with a great community”, “focus on clean code” vs “focus on business outcomes”.</p>
<p>—</p>
<p>So my mind gets <a href="https://frantic.im/side-projects-are-hard/">stuck</a> on this one. How do you pick the best tool for the job?</p>
<p>The only way out of this pickle situation I found so far is to turn around and face the question itself. What does “the best” even mean?</p>
<p>Back to the tree planting, the choice is simple, so it’s obvious which tool is the best. In programming, we no longer have <a href="https://youtu.be/0Ttw9ks05G4?si=XR4z-Jwj825p7fkI&amp;t=222">that luxury</a>, thus maybe the concept of “the best” doesn’t work anymore. The options are just too close, too nuanced, and the consequences are too fuzzy. Even if you are an expert in these tools, there are still enough unknowns to make the choice non-trivial.</p>
<p>When the options can’t be plotted on a single axis with clear “good” and “bad” fits, there’s no “best”. There’s only “good enough”. And if we give up chasing “the best tool for the job”, we might just free up enough mental space to use “the good enough tool” to actually plant that tree.</p>

      ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://frantic.im/opening-mail</id>
      <title>Opening Mail</title>
      <updated>2024-01-06T12:00:00+00:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://frantic.im/opening-mail" />
      <summary>First make the change easy, then make the easy change.</summary>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        
        
        
        <p>I never liked opening envelopes; they’re tricky and ripping them open is annoying. My letters would get stuck or tear with the envelope.</p>
<p>The mail just used to stack up, and I’d miss important stuff because of it.</p>
<p>But then I found this cool little gadget from Japan.</p>
<a style="border: none" href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B001GR4DQ8" target="_blank">
  <img src="https://frantic.im/assets/ceramic-letter-opener.jpg" width="256">
</a>
<p>It’s well-made, affordable, and feels good to use. Plus, it’s safe.</p>
<p>The best part? It actually made me enjoy opening my mail.</p>
<p>After this experience, I started thinking differently about unpleasant tasks. Is there a tool or a service that add delight to mundane things?</p>
<p>I also started noticing when people do this subconiously. For example, most software engineers I know hate blogging, but they like building their own blog engine to make blogging more pleasant (I’m very guilty of this too).</p>
<p>Kent Beck <a href="https://twitter.com/KentBeck/status/250733358307500032">nailed it</a>: “for each desired change, make the change easy (warning: this may be hard), then make the easy change”.</p>

      ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://frantic.im/whos-watching-the-watchdog</id>
      <title>Who&#39;s Watching the Watchdog?</title>
      <updated>2023-11-22T12:00:00+00:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://frantic.im/whos-watching-the-watchdog" />
      <summary>Making reliable systems that expect things to go wrong</summary>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        
        
        
        <p>At my current company we have an automated pipeline for processing customer’s orders. It’s pretty complex — talking to multiple different services, training models, storing large files, updating the database, sending emails and push notifications.</p>
<p>Sometimes things get stuck because of a temporary 3rd party outage or a bug in our code.</p>
<p>So we built a watchdog service: it monitors the stream of orders and makes sure the orders get processed within reasonable timeframe (3 hours). The watchdog only looks at the final invariant — was the order fulfilled and delivered to the customer? It doesn’t care about any intermediary steps.</p>
<p>This system has saved us many times. When the watchdog finds a stuck order, it posts in our special channel in Slack. We investigate the problem and address the root cause, so hopefully we won’t see new orders stuck for the same reason.</p>
<p>But who’s watching the watchdog? What if it fails to run?</p>
<p>It actually happened to us once. The watchdog is running on the job scheduling system, and that system went down. That meant no orders were getting processed and watchdog also wasn’t running. The alerts channel in Slack was blissfully silent.</p>
<p>To address this case, we need a system that can watch the watchdog. We are using these two:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.sentry.io/product/crons/">Sentry Cron</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.checklyhq.com/blog/heartbeat-monitoring-with-checkly/">Checkly Heartbeat</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The idea behind both systems is the same: they expect a regular cron job to “check in” on a pre-defined schedule. If it misses a check-in, there’s likely a problem and we get an alert in Slack.</p>
<p>Complex systems always find surprising ways to fail. When adding an end-to-end quality watchdog (and ways to watch the watchdog) you can create a positive loop of detecting issues and hardening the system.</p>

      ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://frantic.im/hacker-gifts</id>
      <title>A Side Project Story: Hacker Gifts</title>
      <updated>2023-10-29T12:00:00+00:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://frantic.im/hacker-gifts" />
      <summary>This is a story about a side project that I started in 2018, and the reasons I'm shutting it down.</summary>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        
        
        
        <p><em>This is a story about a side project, <a href="https://hacker.gifts/">Hacker Gifts</a>, that I started in 2018, and the reasons I’m shutting it down.</em></p>
<p>February 2018. London, 9 pm. It’s dark outside and raining. Vlad is holding a flashlight and is looking for… something. One hour ago a girl he didn’t know gave him two numbers over the phone and hung up. The numbers looked like GPS coordinates not too far from his house, so Vlad decided to check it out. The people on the street are gazing at Vlad suspiciously, and all he can think about is “How did I get into all of this?”</p>
<p>He got into all of that because of me.</p>
<p>Vlad is my close friend. He has everything (or means of getting everything) that most people would consider a “birthday gift”. I wanted to give him something special that he’ll remember for the rest of his life.</p>
<p>At first, the idea was simple — write a greetings message, encode it as a QR code and send it via mail. But that would have been too easy for Vlad. So, inspired by great movies like <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0119174/">The Game (1997)</a>, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1677720/">Ready Player One (2018)</a> and <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt4158110/">Mr. Robot</a>, I dialed it up.</p>
<p>In the QR-encoded letter I had a link to a file with a private SSH key and an IP address (encoded as an obscure Japanese poem). The server had a Tetris game running on it (Vlad <em>loves</em> Tetris), and once he got through that he saw instructions to send 1 satoshi to a Bitcoin address. After verifying the transaction a script gave him the next SSH key, but this time it was encrypted with a password, and the password was inside of an armv6 binary hosted on IPFS that required a PIN. Bruteforcing the PIN took more than 4 hours on a Raspberry Pi. This time the note instructed Vlad to wait for a phone call. I put the third key on a flash drive and hid it under a bench in a park in London, and asked my cousin to give Vlad a call and tell him the GPS coordinates. The password to the last key was encoded as a Branf*ck program in a BMP file. Using the third key Vlad got to a VNC session on a virtual machine running Windows 3.1, where he had to find a file hidden on a virtual floppy drive. The file had a link to 90s-style webpage with a birthday greeting on it. Happy Birthday, Vlad!</p>
<p><img src="https://frantic.im/assets/hacker-gifts/happy-birthday.jpg" alt="Early version of hacker.gifts website" /></p>
<p>It took me more than 2 months to set this all up. Vlad really liked the experience. I was proud.</p>
<h2>Into production</h2>
<p>If Vlad liked it, maybe others will like it too?</p>
<p>I’ve decided to productionalize my learning and make it so anyone could get a similar puzzle. I really wanted to make the puzzle feel personal: it should know the name of the person who’s solving it, and at the end should reveal a secret message.</p>
<p>At first, I wanted to send physical postcards, but I stumbled on way too many issues. The printing quality was always a problem. During the delivery, USPS scratched the postcard with the QR code and it didn’t always read correctly. Delivery sometimes took more than a week. In addition, many people didn’t want to leave their physical address, and the recipient could mistake the postcard for spam.</p>
<p>I decided to shift the focus exclusively to the digital aspect. Buyers can print it themselves, transfer it to their phone, or hide it on their desktop.</p>
<p><img src="https://frantic.im/assets/hacker-gifts/01-Hacker-Gifts.png" alt="Early version of hacker.gifts website" /></p>
<h2>Tech stack</h2>
<p>I remember wasting <em>a lot</em> of time on which framework to use to build the website. The classic software engineering side project dilemmas. I was agonizing about this until one night I forked $32 for a Shopify store. It wasn’t perfect by my standards, but it definitely unlocked everything else.</p>
<p>At first, I processed all orders manually. Shopify sends me a push notification, I run to the computer and quickly enter the data into a local script, then send the result by mail.</p>
<p>In early days the adrenaline from every $20 brought a thrill. But I quickly got tired of getting up in the middle of the night. In addition, I wanted to create a pleasant impression and instant free delivery.</p>
<p>It was time for <em>Automation</em>. Shopify can call a webhook for each order, and there I can generate a new postcard and send it by mail.</p>
<p>I started with a microservice zoo — a script in Ruby, an AWS lambda in Node.js, order data in DynamoDB, files in S3, Mailchimp, all seasoned with a bit of Zapier. I tried to keep each individual thing very simple, but the result turned out to be a complexity monster. Debugging stuck orders was hell.</p>
<p>When the COVID hit, I <a href="https://frantic.im/back-to-rails">rewrote everything in Ruby on Rails</a>. Because Rails is an established framework, I didn’t need to reinvent the wheel at every step. I’ve got proper tests, queues, database, caching — all working in a nice consistent setup that didn’t rely on 3rd party services.</p>
<p><img src="https://frantic.im/assets/hacker-gifts/tests.png" alt="Sweet Rails tests" /></p>
<h2>Growth and marketing</h2>
<p>When I started, I knew absolutely nothing about growth and marketing.</p>
<p>I remember spending my first $250 on ads — it got me ~200 likes on Facebook and zero orders. I tuned creative, targeting, copy — all with virtually no results. The problem was that I didn’t know how to position and explain my product. But I also <a href="https://medium.com/@andreamantovani/known-knowns-known-unknowns-unknown-unknowns-leadership-367f346b0953">didn’t know I didn’t know that</a>. Frustrating times.</p>
<p>I found my first customers in a local Bay Area group for spouses of software engineers who worked for tech companies. Posting there felt very uncomfortable, but 30 minutes later I sold my first item!</p>
<p>Since then, the product has grown mostly through word-of-mouth and organic Google search.</p>
<p>I struggled with positioning the product until I read <a href="https://www.momtestbook.com/">The Mom Test</a>. That book really opened my eyes to what questions to ask, and I’ve made many improvements to the website since then.</p>
<p>After much trial and error, I have identified two target audiences:</p>
<ul>
<li>Nerds who love side projects and fun puzzles. My product resonated with them once they dug deeper, but getting them to notice it was a challenge — these folks are completely blind to advertising and popular social media.</li>
<li>Regular people who don’t understand the technology, but who want a thoughtful gift for a programmer. They look at Facebook and click on ads, but it’s difficult to convey the value of such a gift.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://frantic.im/assets/hacker-gifts/latest-landing-page.png" alt="Improved hacker.gifts landing page" /></p>
<h2>Costs and profits</h2>
<p>Technically the project is profitable. Here are some numbers from 2020, recent years were in the same ballpark.</p>
<p>Typically I charged $19.99 for a puzzle, sometimes giving a discount.</p>
<p>For the period from September 1, 2019 to September 1, 2020, there were 170 orders, with a total revenue of $3,162.50.</p>
<p><img src="https://frantic.im/assets/hacker-gifts/03-Revenue.png" alt="Improved hacker.gifts landing page" /></p>
<p>Shopify eats ~4% from each transaction, charges $32/mo for the service and $36 for the domain.</p>
<p>The backend needs a server on Heroku ($7/mo), Postgres DB ($10/mo) and one VPS ($10/mo) for the quest + domain ($13/y).</p>
<p>Total expenses: $757.</p>
<p>Profit $3,162.50 - 4% - $757 = $2,279.</p>
<p>On the one hand, it’s very good for a pet project. In 2019, the project barely broke even. 2021-2023 were similar to 2020.</p>
<p>But there’s one set of numbers that I’m really proud of.</p>
<p><img src="https://frantic.im/assets/hacker-gifts/02-Survey.png" alt="Improved hacker.gifts landing page" /></p>
<p>At the end of the puzzle I have a small form for feedback. Not everyone fills it out, but this is what the statistics look like. Reading the feedback always made me smile. I’ve collected some on the <a href="https://hacker.gifts/blogs/guides/testimonials">testimonials</a> page.</p>
<h2>Shutting It Down</h2>
<p>For the last few years, I haven’t touched the project much. But there’s no such thing as a truly passive side project.</p>
<p>I’m always anxious something is going to break and users won’t get their order. I have alerts for errors and watchdogs, but still feel the responsibility to deliver a great experience hanging over my shoulders.</p>
<p>The tech is also not helping: every bit of my stack is aging fast, and without constant support the cost of any change grows. “The Heroku-18 stack is end-of-life” is April next year, but I know if I start updating it, something else will pop up — new Rails version, DB upgrade, certificates, etc. Even with fewer moving pieces than before, maintenance is not trivial.</p>
<p>But the most important reason I’m shutting it down is to give space for new ideas to grow. In its current state, <a href="https://hacker.gifts">Hacker Gifts</a> still occupies my headspace that I could use for other things.</p>
<p>Looking back, this project definitely fits the category of “a solution in search of a problem”. But I don’t blame myself. IMHO the solution is really clever, I haven’t seen anything like this anywhere before. I also really enjoyed building it, and I learned a ton about marketing, customer interviews, ads, and many other things.</p>
<p>If you read this far and would like to try it out for free, use code <code>FRANTIC</code> at checkout <a href="https://hacker.gifts/">here</a>. I’ll keep the servers up until Jan 2024. Also check out <a href="https://robertovaccari.com/blog/2021_02_14_hacker_gifts/">Roberto Vaccari’s</a> review (spoilers!)</p>

      ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://frantic.im/story-behind-hackathon-photo</id>
      <title>Story Behind Hackathon Photo</title>
      <updated>2023-07-04T12:00:00+00:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://frantic.im/story-behind-hackathon-photo" />
      <summary>How a random stream of events ended up creating a picture with 57 million views</summary>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        
        
        
        <p>I’ve seen <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/QBpZGqEMsKg">this photo</a> on the internet, sometimes even billboards and posters. Maybe you’ve seen it too? Here’s the story behind it.</p>
<p><img src="https://frantic.im/assets/hackathon.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>In 2017 I was working on React Native team. We were friends with all other developer experience teams around Facebook. One of them worked on <a href="https://nuclide.io/">Nuclide</a> (RIP), a set of plugins for Atom editor turning it into multi-platform IDE. Nuclide struggled with adoption outside Facebook walls.</p>
<p>Around that time, Unsplash was becoming very popular. They were the first to provide high quality stock photos for free (very bold strategy for its time). Their photos were spreading like a wildfire.</p>
<p>So I had this “genius” idea: make a photo of MacBook Pro with Atom/Nuclide running on it, upload it to Unsplash and get programming blog posts use it as their cover photo (for free). People will notice a cool looking editor and will start asking “what is it?”, eventually finding Nuclide (now you know why I’m not working in marketing).</p>
<p>I took my old Canon 6D to the office and we did a photoshoot. I uploaded the picture (along with others from my Lightroom collection, to make it less sketchy).</p>
<p><img src="https://frantic.im/assets/nuclide.jpg" alt="Nuclide/Atom on MacBook Pro" /></p>
<p>The plan didn’t work. The image got some downloads, but not much. It was lost in a sea of similar pictures. A year later, Facebook gave up on Nuclide and marketing efforts became irrelevant.</p>
<p>However, one thing came out of this process I did not expect.</p>
<p>Together with the Nuclide photo, I uploaded a picture I took that year in Ukraine. I was a judge at <a href="https://www.devchallenge.it/">DevChallenge</a> hackathon in Kyiv, and during the break I snapped a few photos with a wide 24mm lens. I really liked how concentrated everyone was, staff members walking the rows, the uniformity, lighting, stickers on the notebooks. I don’t think the photo was very good by photography standards, but I loved the spirit of that place and wanted to capture it.</p>
<p><img src="https://frantic.im/assets/hackathon_lightroom.png" alt="Other pictures from that hackathon in Kyiv" /></p>
<p>During the uploading process Unsplash asked if I wanted to submit my pictures to their first ever “Unsplash Awards” and I thought “sure why not?”.</p>
<p>I forgot about this for a while, until several months later I got an email from Unspash notifying me that I won <a href="https://awards.unsplash.com/2017/#/tech-and-business">“Unsplash Awards 2017” in “Tech and business”</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In a way, Alex’s photo captures a reflection of modern life: staring at a screen. Our lives, especially in our twenties, feels like a competition. From school, to university, to getting a job and progressing through our careers – it’s a never ending competition. The photo draws your eyes out across the rows of workers, all seemingly identical – but at the same time, showing small hints of color and personality from every worker that highlight and humanizes their unique history and personality. It makes me think of 20 years from now, what technology will be ubiquitous.
– Niv Dror, ProductHunt/Angelist</p>
</blockquote>
<p>They sent me a bunch of cool prizes: PeakDesign Messenger bag, straps and clips, Moment lens for iPhone, and even a printed version of my photo.</p>
<p>Now, looking at it, I do regret not processing the picture more: the horizon line is a bit tilted, you can spot chromatic aberration, the windows are overexposed.</p>
<p>Today that picture has 57 million views and used all over the internet. It even ended up on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21010674">Hacker News</a> with the classic “It looks like a sweatshop” and “exact type of workplace I wouldn’t want anyone to end up” comments.</p>
<p>Conclusions? None, I guess. I just love how a stream of random events brought this to life.</p>

      ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
</feed>